So, the South lost the Civil War, and
that, to put it mildly, was a prodigious
bummer for them. But not to worry,
because a handful of visionaries had
plans to build a new South in the years
following the war. And I reckon we
should check on how new that South
actually was. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milt, let's get to it.
So, like I said, the Confederacy had its
southern hind parts handed to it during
the Civil War, and now they were a
conquered foe attempting to rebuild
their society. And it was generally
accepted among southerners that one of
the chief reasons they had lost the war
was because of the industrial
superiority of the north. And they were
absolutely right about that. Like during
the Civil War, the North possessed about
70% of the nation's railroads and
something like 85% of the nation's
banks. And more to the point, the North
was home to about 90% of the factories
in the United States. Which meant in
practical terms that for every gun the
South manufactured, the North was
manufacturing more than 30 guns. And
look, I don't know much about anything,
but I'm pretty sure that one gun versus
30 is going to be a real disadvantage.
Oh, and by the way, if you want note
guys to follow along with this video and
all my videos, check the link in the
description. So, in light of all of
that, during the reconstruction years,
some southern leaders championed the
idea of a new south defined less by
agriculture and more by industry. And
although several prominent southern
leaders championed this new vision, the
most vocal leader was surely Henry
Grady. He was a journalist from Georgia.
Throughout the 1880s, Grady flapped his
mouth hole tirelessly in speech after
speech, arguing that the new South must
diversify its agricultural output and
more importantly, rapidly develop its
industrial capacity. And fun fact, Grady
actually helped found the Georgia
Institute of Technology, or if you're
sassy, Georgia Tech. And he did that in
order to train southern students in the
skills required for industrial work and
economic growth. And I'm not just
throwing in that tidbit for funsies. No,
it demonstrates that proponents of this
vision meant absolute business about
transforming the South into an
industrial power. And as you might have
guessed, Grady's vision for a new South
was not new in at least one way. Namely,
he argued that white Americans must
always maintain their superiority and
control over black Americans, which, you
know, par for the southern racial
courts. Anyway, the idea of the new
south was a push to achieve economic and
social modernization while keeping the
structures of white supremacy in place.
Okay, so now that we've heard about the
vision, let's see how well it got
accomplished. So, on one hand, there
were some significant strides made to
fulfill the vision of the new south. For
example, mining operations were
established in the Appalachians and
textile factories sprang up in Georgia
and the Carolinas. But perhaps the most
significant example of southern
industrialization was the rise of an
enormously profitable iron and coal
operation in Alabama, founded by Henry
Dearta. So that's nice and all, but
here's where I tell you that on the
whole, the vision for the new south
ultimately failed on account of it's
very difficult to fundamentally change
an entire economy that had been in place
for centuries. Not to mention, the Civil
War devastated the southern landscape,
and their determination to maintain a
labor system that kept black southerners
at the bottom meant there weren't a
whole lot of incentives for innovation
down there. And so, the South remained a
region devoted to agricultural exports
like cotton and tobacco and rice. And
that further meant that the South
continued to perpetuate the dominant
race-based and oppressive labor systems
that supported such economics, namely
sharecropping and tenant farming. So,
while a single tear ran down Henry
Grady's cheek, the rest of the South was
busy trying to revert to their pre-Ivil
War ways. That means it's time to talk
about the wholesale racial segregation
that southerners took pains to develop.
So while the South worked to maintain
its pre-war economic and labor
structures, they also worked to
establish a hierarchical society in
which whites were supreme over blacks.
And this effort, of course, was made all
the more easier after the end of
reconstruction in 1877. And there were
three significant means by which
southerners accomplished this. First, in
the 1890s, southern states passed a
series of black codes that became known
as Jim Crow laws. And these laws
mandated the complete separation of the
white and black races. And you're
probably thinking, "But Himler, didn't
the Civil Rights Act of 1875 ensure that
black Americans had equal rights to
public facilities and prevented election
related violence?" Like, that's what you
were thinking, right? I knew it. But
here's where I tell you, my inquisitive
people, that in 1883, the Supreme Court
ruled on a series of civil rights cases
and declared many of the provisions of
the Civil Rights Act were
unconstitutional. And so, after that law
bit it, southern states had all the
latitude they needed to enact Jim Crow
laws, which mandated that social life
between the two races be entirely
dissociated from one another. And as a
result, children were separated into
black and white schools while every
public facility from buses to bathrooms
were also segregated by race. But the
second means by which southerners
crafted their hierarchical society was
by means of a landmark Supreme Court
decision, namely Py v. Ferguson. So like
don't get the idea that black people in
the south just rolled over and accepted
this profound attack against their
constitutional rights. No, many of them
resisted. And in this case, the man
resisting was named Homer Py. Now, he
was a mixed race man and deliberately
boarded the whites only section of a
rail car in order to challenge the
Louisiana law. And in short order, Pie
was arrested for violating a Louisiana
segregation law mandating that whites
and blacks must ride in separate train
cars. And so in 1896, the case
eventually made it up on appeal to the
Supreme Court where PI's lawyers argued
that the legal separation of the races
violated the equal protection clause of
the 14th amendment. But the court was
not persuaded and ruled that racial
separation is constitutional so long as
the public accommodations are equal,
thus establishing the separate but equal
doctrine. So in essence, the pie case
had the effect of upholding the
constitutionality of Jim Crow laws. And
while white southerners certainly upheld
the separate part of the equation, they
emphatically did not work for the
equality of public facilities for black
Americans. In fact, they took it as a
pass to extend the reach of Jim Crow as
far as humanly possible in order to
maintain control over southern blacks.
And then the third means by which
southerners maintained a racial
hierarchy was by means of scientific
racism. So some southerners justified
and proved the necessity of the
separation of the races by employing
various scientific theories of race that
multiplied wildly during this period and
heavy emphasis on for example in the
first half of the 19th century Samuel
George Morton believed that he could
demonstrate the biological differences
between the races by measuring skulls.
And what he found was that Caucasian
skulls are in general larger than
African skulls which obviously indicated
that white people have greater
intellectual capacity than black people.
Now, later Morton's methods were found
to be entirely corrupt, and it turned
out he falsified his data in order to
prove an assertion he already
desperately wanted to be true.
Regardless, scientific racism provided
Southerners eager to justify their
racial policies a way to feel that their
social domination was actually
beneficial to the blacks whom they
marginalized. So, you know, they were
philanthropists because science. So, now
let's turn the corner and consider the
experience of black Americans in the
South during the Jim Crow era. And there
are two categories you're going to need
to know. First, blacks in the South face
racial discrimination. And I mean, no
duh. But let me explain a couple
specific features of that
discrimination. First of all, in most
southern states, Jim Crow laws
disenfranchise black voters by
introducing pole taxes or literacy tests
or grandfather clauses which prevented
black citizens from voting. But how
could they do that? Says you, since the
15th amendment specifically protected
the right of black men to vote. Well
says I, the Constitution only protected
voting in a general sense, but it had
always been up to the individual states
to decide how the actual process of
voting got done. So in theory, Jim Crow
laws did not diminish the protections of
the 15th Amendment in the slightest.
What they did was to say, "Hey, everyone
is absolutely welcome to vote, but just
to make sure that the integrity of the
election is upheld, voters need to pay a
pole tax or pass a literacy test." And
again, those conditions applied to both
black and white voters in theory. But in
actual fact, the poll taxes and the
literacy tests were mostly waved for
white voters, and the effect was to keep
black people from voting. And then the
second form of discrimination blacks
faced grew out of an elaborate system of
racial social etiquette southerners
developed to promote white superiority.
For example, black people were required
to stand aside if they encountered white
people on the sidewalk. Additionally, in
any place of business, blacks were
required to wait quietly and
submissively until the white customers
were served before conducting their own
business. Okay. Then the second category
you'll need to remember about the black
experience in the late 19th century
concerns the increased violence they
endured. You see, in the last two
decades of the 19th century, hundreds of
black people who challenged Jim Crow
laws became the victims of lynching, in
which white mobs would brutalize and
publicly execute black people who
refused to stay in their place. And by
1950, something like 4,000 lynchings had
occurred in the South. And this kind of
violence was used to reinforce the
structures of racial hierarchy and Jim
Crow and voter suppression. Like, it
wasn't uncommon for people who attended
public lynchings to take pictures of the
execution. And that shows that they
clearly did not expect to face any
punishment from the authorities. Now,
even in the midst of such widespread and
violent attempts to consign black
Americans to the second class of
citizenship, there were not a few
reformers who attempted to change the
system and facilitate black advancement
in the south. However, these reformers
often had very different ideas of what
it meant to fight for racial equality.
And I'll give you two opposing examples.
First, meet Ida B. Wells, who is a
southern black journalist who used her
talents to outright confront the
injustices of black marginalization and
not least the horrors of lynching. And
as a result of her efforts to suggest
that maybe publicly executing black
people was wrong, she received constant
death threats and her opponents
eventually broke into her office and
destroyed her printing equipment. And so
afterward, Wells migrated to the north
where she was by comparison much safer
and she carried on her fight against Jim
Crow from there. But on the other side
of the coin, reformers like Booker T.
Washington argued that the best response
to black oppression and discrimination
was kind of to ignore it. And while
black people were ignoring their
oppression, Washington argued they
should work tooth and nail to get
educated and better themselves
economically. And that way, once blacks
have acquired wealth, that economic
power would eventually turn into social
power. And there were plenty of other
reformers who challenged racial
discrimination during this period. But
on the whole, they would see very little
gains until the middle of the 20th
century. And that means that the new
south was in nearly every way exactly
like the old south. Okay, you can click
here to watch my other videos for unit 6
or you can click here to grab my video
note guides which is going to help you
get all the contents of this course
firmly crammed into your brain fold.
Now, I'm glad you came around and I'll
catch you on the flip-flop. I'm Lur.